so to speed up virtual to physical
translation the processor includes a
structure called the translation
lookaside buffer or TLB the TLB is a
cache for translations so now you would
ask yourself well how is the TLB better
than just using the cache itself well
first the cache is relatively big it
could store a lot of translations if we
only held translations there but we
don't most of the stuff in the cache is
data one translation in the cache covers
a whole page worth of data so the TLB
that cache is only translations can be
extremely small which means extremely
fast let's look for example at a program
that accesses 16 kilobytes of data for
that to work well we need about 16
kilobytes of cache but this is only 4
pages if we have a 4 kilobyte page so
the TLB that corresponds to that only
needs four entries to cover the same
amount of memory and with only 4 entries
we can make the deal be extremely
extremely fast much less than a cycle
for each translation next we have seen
that in a multi-level page table we
access our cache for each level of the
page table because we need to look up
all those entries in order to find the
final translation in contrast till the
only stores the final translation even
if we have a 4 level page table
eventually we find what a given page
number Maps do and we just store the
frame number in the TLB not the
intermediate page table entries that we
have been using to finally come up with
the translation so in a cache we'll have
for a 4 level page table for accesses to
do the translation in a TLB we do this
in one axis so now a load or a store
just needs to form the address access
the TLB to find the translation and then
access the cache to get the data if we
have both the TLB hit and the cache hit
this can be done in one or two cycles
but what if we have a TLB miss what if
we do not find a translation in the TLB
in that case we need to perform the
translation using the page table or page
tables if we have a multiple level page
table and then put that translation in
our TLB so that it can be used later
reiax is the same page again